Herman B Wells House recipes, 1968-1999 and undated C681
Indiana University Archives
Herman B Wells House recipes
1968-1999 and undated
Indiana University Archives
Wells, Herman B
C681
0.8 cubic feet 2 boxes
Herman B Wells served as president of Indiana University from 1937 through 1962 and University Chancellor from 1962 through 2000. In 1964, Wells occupied the house on the corner of 10th Street and Jordan Avenue in Bloomington now known as the Herman B Wells House. This collection contains handwritten and typed recipes and related items that were collected by Wells and individuals employed at the Wells House, including recipes for desserts, appetizers, main and side dishes, salads, and condiments.
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research. Advance notice required.
Historical Note
Herman B Wells served as president of Indiana University from 1937 through 1962 and Chancellor from 1962 through 2000. In 1964, Wells occupied the house on the corner of 10th Street and Jordan Avenue in Bloomington now known as the Herman B Wells House. While living in the house, Chancellor Wells often entertained guests of the university. The recipes in this collection were likely collected by Wells and Lorne Shields, Matilda "Tillie" Hopkins, and other cooks who worked at the house.
Arrangement
The collection is organized into two series: Recipes and Ephemera.
Scope and Content Note
This collection contains recipes and related items found at the former home of Herman B Wells in Bloomington, Indiana. The recipes consist of newspapers and magazine clippings, printed recipe cards, and handwritten recipes. They are mostly for desserts and appetizers but also a number of main and side dishes, salads, and condiments. Of special interest are handwritten recipes and annotated recipes that include comments about Wells' tastes and references to cook Matilda "Tillie" Hopkins.
The collection also includes undated ephemera such as shopping lists, receipts, notes, and menus that were stored with the recipes. Also present are 2 photographs of women formerly employed at the house and the recipe boxes that originally contained the other materials in the collection.
Related Material
Related collections include:
Herman B Wells papers, Collection C75
Indiana University President's Office records, Collection C213
Related photographs may be available in the Indiana University Archives Photograph Collection
This collection does not include the favorite "Herman B Wells cake." That recipe can be found on the University Archives blog at https://blogs.libraries.indiana.edu/iubarchives/2017/06/06/chill-before-slicing-a-recipe-for-herman-b-wells-cake
Acquisition Information
Accession: 2016/004
Provenance
The contents of this collection were found in two recipe boxes in the former residence of Herman B Wells at 1321 East 10th Street, Bloomington, Indiana. They were transferred to the Indiana University Archives by Dixie Mobley in January 2016.
- Recipes, 1968-1999 and undated (Box 1)
  - Appetizers and sides, 1971-1990 and undated (Box 1)
    - Bayou red beans and rice (Box 1)
      Scope and Contents
      Note on recipe: "Send the above to Sharon, Looks good to me. HBW"
    - Cheese and olive balls (Box 1)
      (Ingredients only)
    - Cheese balls (Box 1)
    - Cheese dainties, (2 handwritten copies) (Box 1)
    - Cheese recipe (unlabeled), circa 1982 (Box 1)
    - Dill 'n' onion dip (Box 1)
    - Dip with oyster crackers, dill, and ranch dressing (unlabeled) (Box 1)
    - Guacamole (Box 1)
    - Lemon yogurt dip, 1990 (Box 1)
    - Party Hoppin John (Box 1)
    - Snow Peas Stuffed with Herb Cheese, 1986 (Box 1)
    - Tomato Dumplings (Box 1)
    - Wild Rice (Box 1)
  - Breads, 1975 and undated (Box 1)
    - Banana nut bread, (3 recipes) (Box 1)
    - Bread recipe booklet, 1975 (Box 1)
    - Irish soda bread (Box 1)
    - Jalapeno cornbread muffins (Box 1)
    - Margaret's apple muffins (Box 1)
    - Pumpkin bread (Box 1)
    - Raisin zucchini bread (Box 1)
    - Zucchini bread (Box 1)
  - Breakfast, 1984 and undated (Box 1)
    - Crepe, muffin, pancake and waffle recipes, (1 newspaper clipping containing 5 recipes) (Box 1)
    - French toast with apple custard sauce, October 24, 1984 (Box 1)
    - Grits and cheese (Box 1)
    - Hominy and grits recipes (Box 1)
    - Spinach pie (Box 1)
  - Casseroles, 1986 and undated (Box 1)
    - Baked squash casserole (Box 1)
    - Cheese shrimp casserole (Box 1)
    - Egg casserole (Box 1)
    - Egg Huntington (Box 1)
      Note on recipe: "From old Gosport, Ind. hotel"
    - Grits casserole (Box 1)
    - Hominy casserole (Box 1)
    - Lasagne, 1 typescript and 1 handwritten copy (Box 1)
      Typescript includes inscription: "Tillie"
    - Lima bean broccoli casserole (Box 1)
    - Mushroom seafarers casserole (Box 1)
    - Turkey cassoulet (Box 1)
    - Vegetable lasagne roll-ups (Box 1)
    - Vidalia onion casserole (Box 1)
    - Zuccini casserole, (3 handwritten copies) (Box 1)
  - Desserts, cakes, 1975-1985 and undated (Box 1)
    - Bacardi rum cake, (2 copies) (Box 1)
    - Banana cake (Box 1)
    - Brodfute (Bradfute?) Fruit Cake - 1942, June 7, 1975 (Box 1)
    - Carol's coffee cake, (2 handwritten copies) (Box 1)
    - Coffee cake (Box 1)
    - Creamy nut frosting (Box 1)
    - Fresh peach cake (Box 1)
    - German chocolate cake icing (Box 1)
    - German sour cream cake (Box 1)
    - Jam cake; Caramel fudge icing (Box 1)
      Notes on recipe card: "Maret Garard," "Mrs. John Trumbo (1854-1933) Great-Grandmother"
    - Jiffy cake (Box 1)
    - Lemon cake (Box 1)
    - Lickety split cocoa cake (Box 1)
    - "Mother's" cake recipes (Box 1)
    - Pound cake (Box 1)
    - Pumpkin cake (Box 1)
    - Rhubarb cake (Box 1)
    - Shortcake, (1 newspaper clipping and 1 handwritten recipe) (Box 1)
    - Small cake (Box 1)
    - Sour cream cake (Box 1)
    - Sour cream coffee cake (Box 1)
    - Sour cream nutmeg pound cake; Brown sugar pound cake (Box 1)
    - Sour cream streusel coffee cake, September 4, 1985 (Box 1)
    - Whipping cream pound cake (Box 1)
  - Desserts, frozen, undated, circa 1960s-1990s (Box 1)
    - Creamy frozen lime pie (Box 1)
    - French chocolate silk ice cream; sugar-free frozen dessert; orange sherbet (Box 1)
    - Frozen pudding pops; popsicles (Box 1)
    - Lemon pudding (Box 1)
    - Mocha-date shake (Box 1)
    - Peach sorbet (Box 1)
    - Pumpkin ice cream pie, (2 handwritten copies) (Box 1)
  - Desserts, other, circa 1968-1993 and undated; (folder 1 of 2) (Box 1)
    - Alpine fantasy fudge (Box 1)
    - Apple crisp (Apple candy pie) (Box 1)
    - Betty Crocker holiday cookies (Box 1)
    - Brownies (Box 1)
    - Butter cookies (Box 1)
    - Cheesecake, (1 typescript and 1 handwritten recipe) (Box 1)
    - Chocolate chip cookies (Box 1)
    - Citrus nut topping (Box 1)
    - Cranberry mousse (Box 1)
    - Cream puffs (Box 1)
    - Date and nut bars (Box 1)
      Note on back of recipe: "Re: Wenzel's Menu maker, page 921 (Student Union and Food Service Bldg.)"
    - Date cookies (Box 1)
    - Easy bar cookies (Box 1)
    - Fannie May fudge (Box 1)
    - Fig bars (Box 1)
    - Fool proof fudge (Box 1)
    - Foolproof dark chocolate fudge, circa 1991 (Box 1)
    - Fresh peach cobbler with hard sauce, (1 typescript and 1 handwritten recipe) (Box 1)
      Note on typed recipe: "Keep always"
    - German chocolate cake (Box 1)
    - Ginger-snap cookies, June 5, 1973 (Box 1)
    - Marzipan (Box 1)
  - Desserts, other, circa 1968-1993 and undated; (folder 2 of 2) (Box 1)
    - Old-Fashioned apple dumplings (Box 1)
      Note on recipe: "HBW wants this!"
    - Orange cranberry torte (Box 1)
    - Orange pudding, October 15, 1968 (Box 1)
    - Peach crumb crisp (Box 1)
    - Persimmon pudding, (1 typescript and 3 handwritten recipes) (Box 1)
      Typed copy includes note from Herman B Wells about serving the dish at an event.
    - Philadelphia brand cheesecake, (2 recipes (Box 1)
    - Prune whip (Box 1)
    - Ray Kessler's persimmon roll (Box 1)
    - Rice pudding, (2 handwritten copies) (Box 1)
    - Seven layer cookies (Box 1)
    - Spiced nuts (Box 1)
    - Strawberry preserves, (4 handwritten recipes) (Box 1)
    - Sue's chocolate mousse (Box 1)
    - Valentine sugar cookies, February 20, 1985 (Box 1)
  - Desserts, pies, circa 1987 and undated (Box 1)
    - Cream pie, circa 1987; (2 newspaper clippings with five recipes) (Box 1)
    - Gooseberry pie (Box 1)
    - Lattice raisin pie, May 1983 (Box 1)
    - Pie crust ingredients (unlabeled) (Box 1)
    - Pumpkin pie, (2 recipes) (Box 1)
    - Raisin pie (Box 1)
    - Strawberry pie (Box 1)
    - Strawberry pie (Box 1)
    - Sugar cream pie, (5 recipes) (Box 1)
    - Super easy apple crumb pie (Box 1)
    - Supreme lemon meringue pie (Box 1)
    - Sweet potato apple pie (Box 1)
  - Dressings and sauces, undated, circa 1960s-1990s (Box 1)
    - Balsamic vinaigrette; Mayonnaise (Box 1)
    - Boiled salad dressing (Box 1)
    - Chocolate syrup (from Dorothy Raferts) (Box 1)
    - Dad's salad dressing (citation only) (Box 1)
    - Evelyn's caper salad dressing (Box 1)
    - French dressing, (1 typescript and 2 handwritten copies) (Box 1)
      "Recipe from the kitchen of Elfrieda Lang"
    - Mustard sauce (Box 1)
  - Fruits and vegetables, 1990 and undated (Box 1)
    - Baked acorn squash with apples (from Fran Noyes) (Box 1)
    - Baked corn) (Box 1)
    - Cranberry (Box 1)
    - Creamed new potatoes and peas (Box 1)
    - Grated corn pudding (Box 1)
    - Lemony creamed brussels sprouts and celery, November 1990 (Box 1)
    - Rhubarb juice (Box 1)
    - Scalloped corn (Box 1)
    - Scalloped turnips, (1 typescript and 1 handwritten copy) (Box 1)
    - Steve York's squaw corn; Hubert Schmieder's Frau Schmieder's kartoffel (Box 1)
    - Swiss vegetable medley (Box 1)
    - Turnips au gratin (Box 1)
    - Wilted lettuce (Box 1)
    - Zucchini, (2 recipes) (Box 1)
  - Meats/main dishes, circa 1982-1999, undated (Box 1)
    - Asparagus rarebit toast (Box 1)
    - Baked chicken with orange glaze (Box 1)
    - Baked cornish hen cumberland, 1973 (Box 1)
    - Beef recipe (unlabeled) (Box 1)
    - Beef short rib recipes, June 6, 1982 (Box 1)
    - Chicken breasts, (2 handwritten copies) (Box 1)
    - Chicken diablo (Box 1)
    - Chicken divan (Box 1)
    - Chicken recipe (unlabeled) (Box 1)
    - Country ham (Box 1)
    - Dried beef spread (Box 1)
    - Flank steak glazed with maple mustard; Potatoes, onion, and broccoli (Box 1)
    - Garden harvest chicken pie/potato patch pie, April 14, 1991 (Box 1)
    - Ginger beef stir-fry (Box 1)
    - Hints for serving your ham (Box 1)
    - KFC chicken (instructions only), (fragment) (Box 1)
    - Louis Rich turkey recipes (Box 1)
    - Max's white meat loaf (Box 1)
    - Mini meat loaves (Box 1)
    - Pepper steak (Box 1)
    - Planked steak (Box 1)
    - Quick sukiyaki (Box 1)
    - Roast leg or rack of lamb (Note at end of recipe: "HBW: 5 minutes!") (Box 1)
    - Spinach-stuffed chicken breasts (Box 1)
    - Tarragon chicken (Box 1)
    - Tomatoes stuffed with chicken (Box 1)
  - Multiple recipes, 1982-1999 and undated; (folder 1 of 2) (Box 1)
    This folder includes cards, clippings, and other recipe formats that fall into multiple recipe categories.
    - Carnation recipes, circa 1999 (Box 1)
    - Cucumber soup cold, Chicken casserole (Box 1)
    - Fantastic falafil, Traditional sesame tahini, Tomato dressing, Roquefort sauce (Box 1)
    - Gertie's crab cakes, Apple salad with walnuts and feta, Apple tart, Adobe bread, Pork chops with apples and sauerkraut, Dutch apple bars, Tarte tatin, Apple muffins, November 6, 1991 (Box 1)
    - Greek lamb stir-fry, Cinnamon and spice raisin cake, Candy bar raspberry torte, Szechwan-style chicken, May 1991 (Box 1)
    - Green tomato pie, Green tomato jelly, Carrot and peanut spread, Persimmon pudding, Quick bread pudding (Box 1)
    - Lo-cal eggplant, Eggplant pizza, Eggplant quiche, Ratatouille, 1989 (Box 1)
    - Meat pies, Sausage rolls, Pavlova (Box 1)
  - Multiple recipes, 1982-1999 and undated; (folder 2 of 2) (Box 1)
    - Nutty tofu with rice, Winter fruit salad, Portuguese cod for clay pot, Salmon chowder, circa 1983 (Box 1)
    - Oriental beef and broccoli stir-fry, Patty shell vegetable nests (Box 1)
    - Puff pastry shell recipes (Box 1)
    - Rabbit fried with grapefruit juice, Rabbit sausage, Rabbit soup (Box 1)
      Note on recipe: "Tillie"
    - Richard Means' Mama's bread pudding, Antonion Pologruto's Breast of chicken marsala (Box 1)
    - Ruby Red Grapefruit recipes (Box 1)
    - StarKist recipes, 1992 (Box 1)
    - Sweet potato pie, Florence's fruit and jam cake, 22 Nov 1982, November 22, 1982 (Box 1)
    - Wolferman's Original English Muffins recipes (Box 1)
    - Zucchini with lemon and parmesan; Chicken breasts with curried vegetables, 1991 (Box 1)
  - Salads, slaws, relishes, and pickles, 1986, 1991, undated (Box 1)
    - Baked chicken salad, 2 handwritten copies (Box 1)
    - Bread and butter pickles (Box 1)
    - Cabbage slaw (Box 1)
    - Cinnamon applesauce salad (Box 1)
      "Recipe from the kitchen of Bettie Harting"
    - Corn and tuna salad (Box 1)
    - Curry pickles (Box 1)
    - Do-ahead fruit slaw (Box 1)
    - Dutch potato salad (Box 1)
      Notes on recipe: "Boone Co. Cookbook, Amy Buchanan," "For Tillie"
    - German potato salad (Box 1)
      Notes on recipe: "Brown County Cookbook," "For Tillie"
    - Grapefruit and spinach salad (Box 1)
    - Green fruit compote (Box 1)
    - Hominy salad (Box 1)
    - Julie's quick chicken salad (Box 1)
    - Kiwi, orange and grapefruit salad with poppyseed dressing, 1991 (Box 1)
    - Pear Salad (Box 1)
    - Pickle recipe (unlabeled) (Box 1)
    - Potato salad from "Heloise" column, June 18, 1986 (Box 1)
    - Relish, grandma's (Box 1)
    - Saffron rice salad (Box 1)
    - Tomato relish (Box 1)
  - Seafood, undated, circa 1960s-1990s (Box 1)
    - Sen. Stennis' catfish recipe, 1 newspaper clipping and 1 handwritten copy (Box 1)
    - Beer batter, 1 typescript and 1 handwritten copy (Box 1)
    - Chambo mousse, 2 handwritten copies (Box 1)
    - Great grated scampi (Box 1)
    - Lobster Newbury (Box 1)
    - Oyster stew, Oyster stew lyonese, Oyster-corn fritters (Box 1)
    - Oyster pie (Box 1)
      Recipe is circled with note: "Please try for Dr. Wells"
    - Seafood brochettes (Box 1)
  - Soups, undated, circa 1960s-1990s (Box 1)
    - Chili con carne (Box 1)
      From Fran Noyes
    - Corn chowder (Box 1)
    - Gazpacho soup (Box 1)
    - Lobster bisque (Box 1)
    - Madeline soup (Box 1)
    - Potato soup (Box 1)
      "From the recipe file of Marjorie White"
    - Quick Italian beef and vegetable soup (Box 1)
- Ephemera, 1977-1993 and undated (Box 2)
  - Photographs of Mary Jo Thomas (Longstreet) and unidentified woman, undated; (photocopy of 2 Polaroid prints) (Box 2)
    Location of originals
    Original photographs are housed with the IU Archives Photograph Collection.
  - Receipts, notes, and menus, 1977-1993 and undated (Box 2)
  - Recipe divider cards, undated (Box 2)
  - Recipe boxes, undated; (1 metal box and 1 cardboard fruitcake box) (Box 2)